So welcome back.
It's a great honor to introduce a mathematical legend.
John Milnor, who as an undergraduate showed that the integral of the curvature of a knot
was at least four pi, and became very famous as a result,
won the Fields Medal at the age of 31, was professor at Princeton and the Institute for Advanced Study,
and is now director of the Center for Mathematical Research at Stony Brook,
and is a recipient of many honors, including the National Medal of Science,
We'll introduce the next speaker.
Jack Milnor, go ahead.
Well, it's a great pleasure to introduce Vladimir Voevodsky.
Voevodsky began his mathematical career in Moscow, and then came here to Harvard as a junior fellow,
and after a few years at Northwestern, is now at the Institute for Advanced Study.
And as you all know, he was recently awarded a Fields Medal for his work on motivic homotopy theory.
This is a marvelous development which introduces ideas and methods from homotopy theory into pure algebra,
and gives an essential new tool for solving algebraic problems.
So it's a great pleasure to introduce Voevodsky.
Hello, thank you very much for, thank you, Jack, for the introduction.
So I was given by Arthur sort of an impossible task.
I was requested to explain motivic homotopy theory so that it will be understood by non-mathematicians.
So whatever came out of it, you'll see now,
but I don't guarantee that it will be now understandable by either mathematicians or non-mathematicians.
So what there was at first, so at first there were spaces.
So mathematicians were studying spaces and starting with simple examples of spaces.
So one of the most basic spaces is a point.
There is one which is even more basic, but it's hard to draw.
Another one is standard space, which I will have to talk about, is a unit interval.
So an interval of the real line, a line between 0 and 1.
The third example here on the picture is some example of a space of dimension 2.
It's supposed to look like some baking good with two holes in it.
So the last example is more sophisticated, and I want to include it here.
It's a more sort of mathematical example of a space.
It's a space of all n by n matrices with complex entries and with non-zero determinant.
That would be a sophisticated space of dimension n, well,
depending on how you count, n square or 2n square.
So there are many different axiomatizations of the notion of a space in mathematics.
For instance, there are topological spaces, there are metric spaces.
At the end, it all doesn't matter.
As long as one only considers non-pathological examples,
it all comes to the same thing.
So I will assume that there is some intuitive understanding of what space is.
That such understanding is present.
So any space, if you formalize it, really write down a definition,
it will be a tremendously infinite object.
So it's very difficult to work with.
So to distinguish spaces mathematically, we use what we call invariance.
So something more understandable, more finite, typically,
than the space itself associated to a space.
So there are two invariants which I will dare to call the most fundamental ones.
One is the dimension of a space.
So we have dimension zero for a point and dimension one for the interval.
And another invariant is the number of pieces the space consists of.
So in this picture, again, the point consists of one piece.
You cannot divide it into two disconnected pieces.
And then there is something below the point which is sort of a deformed circle
with some deformed interval sitting inside,
but it consists of two different pieces, two disjoint pieces.
There's a circle and there's an interval.
So the number of pieces is another invariant of a space.
Typically, when one thinks of a space,
one thinks of a space which has only one piece.
But that's just a custom.
So what is homotopy theory about?
What it does, it basically studies...
Oh, I need to say something.
Let's call pi zero over space the set of its pieces.
So if space has two pieces, then pi zero is a set of two elements,
namely these pieces.
So it's typically much more finite than the space itself.
What homotopy theory does, it studies some fancy versions of this invariant,
which are called higher homotopy sets.
Now, I will try to explain how one gets to these pi n's,
where pi n will be some set for any integer n,
for any, excuse me, non-negative integer n,
how one gets to pi n from pi zero.
The first thing which I need to...
It can be done in different ways.
So I choose to base my explanation on the notion of a continuous map,
which will also play a fundamental role further.
So what is a continuous map?
So I have a space.
This I cannot show on the projection.
I have a space n, m, and a space n.
And a map from one to another is any rule
which assigns to point of the first space
and point of the second space.
The easiest way, of course, to understand it
is by looking at examples.
And the idea that it's continuous means
that if something was close,
then it doesn't get too far apart.
So let's denote by c of m, n
the set of all continuous maps from m to n.
And we'll see again, by example, what it is.
If I'm looking at continuous maps
from a point to any space,
so what is a map from a point to a space?
It's just determined by where this unique point goes.
So a map from a point to a space
is the same as a point on this space.
So the set of maps from the point to any space
is just a set of points of this very same space.
Another example is what is the set of maps
from any space to a point?
There's only one place for all the points
of the first space to go,
namely this only point on the target space.
And there's always only one map
from any space to the point.
So that's example number two.
Here is a more fancy example.
Let's look at maps
from the unit interval,
the interval of the real line,
to any space.
So it will have some beginning
where the point zero goes
or point one goes,
and then there will be all the points
where all the numbers between zero and one go.
So the fact that it's a continuous map
means that this gadget will have no breaks in it.
That's what it intuitively means.
So the set of all continuous maps
from the interval to any space
is just a set of paths inside this space.
Now let's go back to the notion
of the number of pieces of a space.
How can we say formally
when two points lie in the same piece?
So if they lie in the same piece,
then they can be connected by a path.
In different pieces,
there's no way you can find a path
without breaks which connects one point to another.
So to define formally
what it means for two points to belong to the same piece,
one can use this notion of a path,
of a continuous map from interval to the space.
So let me repeat myself again.
So the only thing which one needs to know
to define the set pi zero of n,
the set of pieces,
is to know what are points and what are paths
between these points.
Well, this is a little bit more fancy,
and maybe I'm not able to explain it as good.
Now here I'm moving to the next invariant,
next homotopy set pi one.
As I said, pi zero is the starting point
of an infinite series of homotopy sets.
So what one does for pi zero,
one takes points
and identifies sort of those
which can be connected by a path.
Now suppose I fix two points, P and Q.
Now let's consider all the paths which connect them.
Suppose they land the same piece,
so there is some path which connects them.
Let's look at all paths.
So we get some space of paths, whatever that means.
Let's try to understand how many pieces
this space of paths has,
and call this set of pieces the pi one
of my original space relative to points P and Q.
So in practice what one has to do
is to consider now continuous maps from a square.
If I have a square mapping to the space,
and let's say I request to have a map
which contracts this side completely to point P
and this side completely to point Q.
Then the image of this side will be a path
going from P to Q,
and the image of this side will also be a path
which is going from P to Q.
And as I move from this side to this side continuously,
I can think of it as being a path between the paths.
So it's continuous deformation between the paths.
So it generates...
Now I can consider the set of pieces
of the space of paths
where two paths are declared
to belong to the same piece
if they can be connected by such a map from a square.
Now this is a procedure which can be repeated,
and then I can use cubes to connect maps from squares
and so on, and one gets a sequence of sets
which are called homotope sets over space.
Now...
Well, I'm sorry, that's what I just said.
There is one nice example which I want to give.
If we try to define these homotope sets
for the space of complex matrices
with a non-zero determinant,
it's, of course, a very complicated problem
how to compare the homotope sets
with the space of complex matrices
with a non-zero determinant.
It's, of course, a very complicated problem
how to compute such a weird thing for such a weird space.
However, it turns out that it can be done,
and the answer,
at least when we consider matrices which are very, very big,
n by n, where n is very large,
the answer turns out to be wonderfully simple.
It's the first homotope set is the point.
Any two matrices can be connected by a path,
and there's only one piece in the whole space of matrices.
If I consider paths,
then it turns out that the pieces in the space of paths
are numbered by integers.
So pi 1 is a set of integers...
I'm sorry, did I...
I made a mistake writing this page.
It has to read like this.
Pi 0 is a star.
Or did I?
No, no, no, sorry.
So pi 1 can be identified with the set of integral numbers.
Pi 2 is again just one point.
Pi 3 is again the set of integral numbers.
And then it goes on like that for a very long time.
For how long exactly depends on number n over there.
But basically if n is infinity, then it goes on forever.
And that's called what periodicity theorem.
There was one of the very impressive achievements
of mathematics in early 60s, late 50s.
I don't know the history well enough.
But that was one of the really first big computations
of homotopy theory.
So that's what I wanted to say about homotopy theory.
It studies spaces.
It associates to them the homotopy sets,
which come from studying paths of paths and so on.
And here is an example of computation.
These are actually things which can be computed
in some non-trivial cases.
Now I want to jump somehow and do something similar
in algebraic setting.
So there is only one way to do it.
And I don't know how much I will have time to say today.
But there is one topic which I want to talk about very quietly
and without hurry.
So that's something which I never saw it even mentioned
in any popular book about mathematics.
I saw algebraic equations mentioned.
I saw homotopy groups probably even mentioned,
especially for elementary books in topology.
But I think that at the heart of 20th century mathematics
lies one particular notion.
And that's the notion of a category.
So let me try to explain what it is about.
So it's a very formal gadget.
And I will illustrate it by an example.
So here are two examples of categories.
Let's forget about the second one for a moment.
Just look at the first one.
So here I have a picture of a category with three objects,
A, B, C.
Now there are arrows between those objects,
which are called morphisms.
And then there is the rule, which says that if I have one arrow
and then it's followed by another arrow,
then there is a third arrow.
Let's say if I have an arrow from A to B
and arrow from B to C,
then there is a rule to get from such a pair
an arrow from A to C.
That's called the composition rule.
But let's even forget this third part for a second.
It's not necessarily important for intuitive understanding.
Main thing which exists in categories
is that there are objects and there are morphisms.
There is a formal set.
In this case, the set of A, B, C,
which is called the set of objects.
For every pair of objects,
there is another formal set.
In this case, it's X and Y between A and B,
Z between B and C, and T between A and C,
which are called morphisms between these objects.
Now the first example is an example
of a combinatorial finite category.
Here is a second example.
Objects are spaces, all spaces which exist.
Morphisms between two spaces
are continuous maps between these spaces.
And of course continuous maps can be composed.
So that gives an example of a category
of a very different kind.
And what was somewhat amazing for me personally
and an amazing discovery is that almost,
let's say for very many classes of mathematical objects,
there are natural categories which correspond to them.
So for most classes of mathematical objects,
we can construct a category whose objects
will be these objects.
Morphisms will be some natural ways
of connecting one object of this type to another,
and there will be some kind of composition.
Sorry.
So here is a more formal way to see what a category is.
So there is a set of objects.
For any pair of objects, there is a set of morphisms
from this object to, between these two objects.
And then there is some composition rule.
Now, what I hope to do now is to show how such a,
well, let's see, how does it work?
Why is it interesting?
Let's, for instance, consider the category
of topological spaces.
And let's take, let's choose a space N.
What can we say about this space?
Looking at it exclusively as being an object
of the category of spaces.
So I don't want to look inside of this space.
I know nothing about its insides.
I only know continuous maps relating this space
to all other spaces.
So instead of looking on the structure of the object,
you look at his sort of social relationship.
The very first example, can we figure out
when the space is a point?
To this, there is a nice answer.
When a space is a point, if and only if
for any other space, there is a single morphism
to this one.
So that characterizes the point completely,
exclusively by morphisms to and from it.
Let's ask a more complicated question.
When is a space N connected?
So when it consists of only one piece.
Or more generally, can we somehow express,
let's say the very first homotopia set,
the set of pieces, purely in categorical terms?
It turns out that yes, we can.
So let's try to play this game.
So first of all, we know what is the set of points
of the space.
It's the set of morphisms from the point to this space.
And we have already characterized the point
in some internal way.
Now, let's consider the unit interval.
The set of maps from the unit interval, morphisms
from the unit interval to the space, is the set of paths.
Now, I need to know what is the beginning of the path
and what is the end of the path.
For that, I need the notion of a composition of morphisms.
So if I have a path, I have two distinguished points, 0 and 1,
on the unit interval, which are morphisms from the point
to the unit interval.
If I look at the composition, my path composed
with one of these points, I get a point of the space,
which is the beginning or the end of the path.
So using purely the structure of the category,
I know what is the set of points.
I know what is the set of paths.
And I know how to assign beginning and end to a path.
So now I can say what is the set of pieces,
because it's simply I have to identify two points which
can be connected by a path, in other words,
for which there is a path such that it's beginning and end.
And that gives me the set pi 0.
So the only thing which is here, which is not internal
to the category of categorical structure,
is the unit interval itself.
We don't know how to characterize it from the inside.
But as soon as I have a category and something which
I want to call the unit interval with two maps,
A and B, called beginning and end,
I can define some kind of pi 0.
How good this definition will be?
It's a big question.
So similarly, if I want to compute the next homotopy set,
here I'm not going in that much detail.
But what I will need to know will be the object point,
the object called unit interval.
And then I'll need to know to have some distinguished object
which is called the square.
And some finite number of morphisms
connecting these objects.
As soon as I have such a purely combinatorial structure
inside my category, I can consider morphisms
with values in any object and get something which
I will call pi 0 and pi 1.
I can continue that and model formally in any category.
Basically, for what I'm talking about,
it's enough to understand pi 0.
And the rest is just not to look too elementary.
So one can formalize the situation
when one has point, interval, square, cube,
cube of the next dimension, and so on.
Now all these things in usual topological world
map to each other.
There are two maps from the point to the interval,
the beginning and the end.
There are four maps from the interval to the square,
the four sides of the square.
There are six maps from the square to the cube,
the six sides of the cube, and so on.
They satisfy some relations.
So I can formally say, let's take any category whatsoever.
Let's take a series of objects and morphisms between them,
satisfying appropriate conditions.
Let's call such a gadget a cubical object.
So as soon as I have a cubical object in any category,
I can play the game which I sort of explained
for pi 0 and pi 1 and define some kind of homotopy sets
for any other object in this category.
Of course, it needs to be said that in most cases
it's not going to work very well,
but it will work somehow.
Now let's go to the next...
So of course that was just an example.
In principle, there are many more structures,
let's say in topological spaces,
which are needed for homotopy theory.
So one can translate most of the structures
into categorical terms,
as I tried to show in this example of cubical spaces.
And then as soon as they are translated
into these formal categorical terms,
one can try to take some very different category
and apply it there and see what happens.
So material homotopy theory happens
when one applies this kind of procedure
to the following category of algebraic equations,
systems of algebraic equations,
which I'm going to describe in a moment.
That's not exactly the standard approach to algebraic geometry,
but that's the most elementary one which I could think of.
So let's consider the following objects,
which we call systems of algebraic equations.
So by definition, a system of algebraic equations
is the following gadget.
It's first of all a list of letters
which are called variables of the system,
and second of all some list of polynomials in these variables
which are called equations of the system.
So here is an example.
There is one variable X
and one equation X squared plus one.
Here is another example.
There are N variables, X1, XN,
and there are no equations whatsoever.
That's a very important system which is denoted by AN.
Here is a more sophisticated example.
I'm sorry, I was getting late writing it,
and it's not probably very readable.
I have N squared variables.
I'm thinking about them as about entries in a matrix
plus one additional variable which I call T.
And I have one equation which says
it's the determinant of this matrix times T minus one.
Well, it doesn't say anything, but that's my equation.
That's my polynomial.
And such a system of equations I want to denote by GLN.
Now, let's define morphisms.
Oh, I need to say something else.
So now I want to try to define
the category of systems of algebraic equations.
So what I need first are
objects, and as objects I will take...
I want to sort of say let's consider
all systems of algebraic equations,
but that's a bit too many.
So a typical approach is we first choose
what kind of coefficients are we going to consider.
So let's take some system of coefficients,
integral numbers or real numbers or complex numbers,
and consider all systems with the same coefficients.
And consider all systems with coefficients
in this type of numbers.
That will be the class of objects of our category.
Now I need morphisms from one system to another.
So I tried to write it down,
and it's difficult to read on a projector.
So by morphism I want to mean a change of variables.
So a morphism from one system in variables x
to another system in variables y
is going to be some way to express variables y
through variables x, such that the equations
sort of are satisfied on both sides.
There is some obvious way to compose these things.
It wasn't I who invented this.
I don't know who invented it,
but I read it in a wonderful textbook
by Manin on algebraic geometry,
which was published in Soviet Union
in the end of the 60s.
So here is an example.
Let's consider A0.
So remember A0 is...
Let me do it this way.
A0 is a system of no equations and no variables.
So a morphism from such a system
would mean that I have to find expressions of my x1, xn
in terms of no variables whatsoever.
So it means I have to replace them by constants,
and the equations still have to be satisfied.
So such a morphism is exactly a solution
of my system of equations.
So morphisms from A0 to x
are solutions of the system of equations.
Similarly, one can verify that morphisms from x to A0,
there's always only one morphism.
So these objects An,
these systems sort of with no equations,
they form a cubical object in a very naive sense.
One can easily build all the maps
which exist between usual cubes.
One can build them between these systems.
And so I can use this cubical object
to define some kind of homotypic groups
for any system of algebraic equations.
In general, I will get...
Sorry, homotypic sets.
In general, I will get not quite correct results,
but there is an example.
If I apply it to the system GLN,
I will actually get very, very reasonable things.
I will get sets which are called algebraic K groups
of the original system of coefficients.
And these groups were defined in many difficult ways
over the last, I don't know, 40 years.
And they're still a source of great many
interesting mathematical problems and insights.
This is something which really depends on key.
So for integers, it will have something to do
with number theory and arithmetics.
For complex numbers or real numbers,
there are connections with special functions
such as polylogarism and hyperbolic geometry,
and I don't know what else.
So these are very, very interesting groups.
And sort of this is an example of how such a game
can lead us to actually objects
which are of independent interest.
So now let me have the last slide
and get a little philosophical.
And so that's how I see the whole picture.
Let me start with geometry,
category of topological spaces.
We invent something about this geometrical world
using our basically visual intuition.
The notion of pieces comes exclusively
from visual intuition.
We're somehow abstracted and rewrite it
in terms of category theory,
which provides this connecting language.
And then we apply it in a new situation,
in this case in the situation of algebraic equations,
which is purely algebraic.
So what we get is some fantastic way
to translate geometric intuition
into results about algebraic objects.
And that's, from my point of view,
the main fun of doing mathematics.
Thank you.
Applause